19437 Ellington Trail Farmington, MN 55024 (651) 983-9268 (cell) myrna.barthel@gmail.com https://www.linkedin.com/in/myrna-barthel-2560486

PROFESSIONAL PROFILE

Highly motivated and experienced professional with extensive experience in leading effective technology teams. Possesses strong executive leadership skills that are balanced with project/program management, business analysis and technical talents to exceed desired management expectations. Utilizes extensive communication skills, the ability to effectively facilitate and manage processes and priorities, and a commitment to do whatever it takes to achieve results.

CAREER SKILLS

- Strategic technology planning
- Fiscal management and budgeting
- Staffing, administration, and employee retention
- Portfolio Management and process management
- Program/Project management and staff development
- Proven leadership, negotiation and analysis skills

- Product Management
- Large-scale systems implementation
- Contract negotiation
- Vendor management
- Acquisition integration
- Enterprise Integration

CAREER ACHIEVEMENTS

- As an independent consultant, was the interim CIO for Sun Country Airlines, directing a technology portfolio that supports a \$550+ million organization. I am also responsible for managing a budget of \$20 million and a staff of over 70 employees and consultants. This is in addition to performing duties as Senior Director, Enterprise Portfolio Management Office (EPMO).
- Previously, I was the interim CIO for Hallmark Business Connections, responsible for managing a technology portfolio
 that supported a \$100+ million organization. Additional responsibilities included managing a \$12 million budget and a
 staff of over 50. These tasks were delivered while performing duties as Director of Application Delivery and Shared
 Services.
- Mentor for Hallmark Business Connections leadership team members utilizing Harvard ManageMentor online program
- Received 85% on Kenexa Employee Engagement Survey with 100% results for Manager Effectiveness
- Responsible for delivery of a single Automated Decisioning Engine for GMAC Rescap. For example, the platform funded \$113 billion a year.
- Managed IT department budgets of up to \$24 million and team sizes of up to 60-70 professionals.
- Directed the Project Management team responsible for delivering financial services solutions and the Project Management Office (PMO) team that is responsible for project standards and processes.
- Orchestrated vendor/product selection and contract negotiations for an enterprise-wide customer relationship management (CRM) system. Efforts resulted in an agreement with Siebel Systems, Inc. to deliver a \$10.2 million, 15,000 user solution.
- Responsible for functional design of a payment system initiative that consolidated multiple credit card accounting systems onto a single, cost-effective platform.
- Planned and directed several conversion activities as they related to consumer credit card acquisitions. Portfolio sizes ranged from 160,000 to 871,000 accounts.
- Managed development staff of 25 who provided enhancements to consumer credit card system. Responsible for managing the development budget of \$5 million.

Myrna Barthel, PMP

19437 Ellington Trail Farmington, MN 55024 (651) 983-9268 (cell) myrna.barthel@gmail.com https://www.linkedin.com/in/myrna-barthel-2560486

CAREER EXPERIENCE

MBarthel Consulting, Minneapolis, Minnesota:

Feb, 2017 – March, 2019

Management Consulting

As a Consultant for Sun Country Airlines, was the Program Manager responsible for leading process improvement and cost savings initiatives to improve operational efficiencies and fuel conservation. Also, led the MSP operations vendor outsourcing and seasonal staffing. Requested by the President to lead this initiative in a 3-month timeline to replace the current vendor. This included an RFP to source a new vendor, hiring new seasonal staff to ensure the operation was staffed until vendor transition, and managing the transition to the new provider.

Interim CIO & Sr. Director, ePMO

For over a year was the interim CIO & Sr. Director, ePMO in the airline industry, reporting to the Chief Executive Officer. Responsibilities include:

- · Leading the effort to centralize the company's technology organizations and capabilities.
- · Developing and advancing customer-facing and digital capabilities to create an extraordinary customer experience.
- · Delivery of a strategic project portfolio, and development of an appropriate technology capability and team to deliver the company's strategic objectives.
- · Leading a team of 70+ IT professionals.

Recent accomplishments include:

- · Delivered organizational and operational efficiencies resulting in \$2 million in annual savings year over year. (e.g. workforce reduction efforts resulting in \$500K in annual savings)
- · Development of a security program and upgrading the airline's security posture to bring them into PCI Compliance.
- · Efforts to implement a Business Continuity Plan (BCP) and Disaster Recovery (DR) Program for the airline.
- Implementation of competitive sourcing best practices and standardized templates for IT procurement. This resulted in an annual savings of \$250K during the most recent network (data/voice) vendor contract negotiations.

Hallmark Business Connections (HBC), Minneapolis, Minnesota:

2008 - 2017

Interim CIO (Jul through Sept 2009 and Sept 2015 through Feb 2016)

On an interim basis, was responsible for strategically supporting the existing technology as well as planning, developing and executing new initiatives. Specific duties included portfolio management, strategic planning for IT and operational excellence, budget, and staff management.

Director, Application Delivery and Shared Services

Managed and supervised four technology leader/managers who are responsible for the activities of a team of 30 IT professionals. The team consisted of Project Managers, Systems Architects, Business Analysts, Software Engineers and Quality Assurance personnel. Responsibilities included managing information systems strategies with focus on Product Management, the HBC project portfolio, and budget for the Product Development & Shared Services IT Department. Worked with Business and IT executive teams on company and department strategies.

GMAC ResCap, Minneapolis, Minnesota:

2000 - 2008

Business Information Officer, Residential Funding Corporation (GMAC/RFC)

Managed and supervised five managers who were responsible for the activities of a team of 60 IT professionals. The team consisted of Project Managers, Systems Architects, Systems Analysts, Developers, Support, and QC personnel. Responsibilities included managing information systems strategies, the IT project portfolio, and budget for the eCommerce Department. Worked with Business and IT executive teams on optimal department strategies.

Myrna Barthel, PMP

19437 Ellington Trail Farmington, MN 55024 (651) 983-9268 (cell) myrna.barthel@gmail.com https://www.linkedin.com/in/myrna-barthel-2560486

Decision Support Engine (DSE) Implementation Manager, Residential Funding Corporation (GMAC/RFC)

Led the creation of a 20-person DSE Implementation team that delivered a strategy and results to create a new product line. The product provided GMAC/RFC with a competitive advantage and additional revenue by selling customized decisioning technology to lender clients.

Program Manager, Residential Capital (GMAC ResCap)

Translating business strategies into a comprehensive Automated Decisioning (AD) Program. Partnering with Business and IT Managers to create enterprise AD roadmaps and release plans. In addition, coordinating and managing the overall AD portfolio, cross-platform & stakeholder collaboration & coordination, change management, resource planning, risk management, program communication and reporting.

Project Manager, Residential Funding Corporation (GMAC/RFC)

Managed e-Commerce projects involved in AssetWise enhancements. AssetWise is an automated underwriting tool designed to give RFC clients a competitive advantage by providing electronic underwriting through the transfer of loan applications and credit reports. Managed activities across multiple internal applications to enhance AssetWise. Responsibilities included work distribution to a staff of 13, project planning and monitoring, coordinating and scheduling system requirements, ensuring project team adherence to process and procedures and managing sponsor expectations for a team budget of \$2.2 million.

U.S. Bank, St. Paul, Minnesota:

1992 - 2000

Manager, Electronic Payment Services

As a Manager, responsible for the overall management of the Electronic Payment Services technical projects. Responsibilities include development and dissemination of methodologies, processes and tools, providing senior project management direction of all Electronic Payment Services technical projects, and managing the department budget.

Group Development Manager, Business Technology Center

As a Development Manager, managed and supervised the activities of 10 to 25 team members, and managed production support and system/acquisition enhancements for issuer and acquirer applications. Responsibilities included on-going prioritization, resource allocation and execution of development, maintenance and regulatory efforts.

Senior Project Manager, Business Technology Center

As a Senior Project Manager, responsible for the on-going planning and direction for the Central Server Computing Project Management department, including the management of account initiation, relationship management, issuer and acquirer systems. Responsibilities included coordination of prioritization activities with users on roughly 100 projects, work distribution for a staff of 18 on more than 30 concurrent projects, project planning and monitoring, coordinating and scheduling system support requirements, departmental direction and staffing needs, ensuring project team adherence to process and procedures, managing exceptions, managing department budgeting process, and communicating regularly with executive management.

Project Lead, Business Technology Center

As a Project Lead, managed and supervised the activities of fifteen team members, and provided production support and system enhancements to an account origination system. Responsibilities included project management, estimating, development, business analysis, technical design and consultation, test plan development, testing and implementation.

Electronic Data Systems Corporation (EDS)

1985 - 1992

Systems Engineer, GMAC, Detroit, MI

As a Systems Engineer, duties included analysis and development of application systems for the GMAC Executive Office reporting needs and Demand notes. Responsibilities included development of both on-line and batch programs, and assistance with project planning duties.

(651) 983-9268 (cell) myrna.barthel@gmail.com https://www.linkedin.com/in/myrna-barthel-2560486

AWARDS/DESIGNATIONS/ORGANIZATIONS

- Received HBC Crowning Achievements Awards 2015 Leading the Way, 2012 Solution Innovation, 2008 Customer Focus
- Network of Executive Women (NEW) Member 2015 to 2016
- Board Member Spare Key November, 2005 to March, 2007
- Member Women's Executive Network
- Received GMAC/RFC Partner Award for continuous accomplishment
- Received GMAC/RFC Celebrate Leadership Award for outstanding performance
- Earned **Project Management Professional (PMP)** designation September, 2002
- Member The Minnesota Chapter of the Project Management Institute (PMI) March, 2000
- Nominated by U.S. Bank senior management to participate in MenTTium 100, the nation's first comprehensive crosscompany executive development program for mid-level business women.
- Awarded U.S. Bank Five Star in recognition of teamwork, quality and outstanding performance

EDUCATION/PROFESSIONAL DEVELOPMENT

University of St. Thomas, St. Paul, Minnesota:

Online Mini MBA Program Certification - 2014 Course work in Business Administration with emphasis on Finance

Dale Carnegie, Edina, Minnesota:

Leadership Training for Managers Effective Communications and Human Relationships High Impact Presentations

Milwaukee Business Technical Institute, Milwaukee, Wisconsin:

Certificate in Data Processing